So, we're discussing if the spiders that
we consume while we sleep really do
control our brain.
Now, we're not doing that. We're doing
what? We're discussing that again. Why?
Oh, they didn't like the first video.
Was I wearing my shirt inside out again?
Oh, they brought up some good critiques.
Well, excuse
me. I guess we're discussing lean mass
hyperresponders again. Second edition,
revised edition. Now, I released a video
earlier in the week or last week
relative to whenever this video gets
released, wherein I broke down the
newest lean mass hyperresponder study.
Don't worry, I'll explain what that is
in a second. And due to a combination of
my oversight and some going on in the
social media world, especially on
Twitter or X as literally no one likes
to call it, that I was made aware of. I
received some excellent critique which
prompted me to take down that video and
here we are again to correct some
mistakes and add some new information.
So, thank you for the resources and
let's discuss this study again. Okay,
the crux of the matter is that a group
of researchers wanted to find out if
there was a relationship between apo
containing particles like lowdensity
lipoproteins that circulate through our
blood vessels and arterial plaque. More
poignantly, if a particular subset of
people called lean mass hyperresponders
or LMHRs still develop arterial plaque
like the rest of us mere mortals. To be
defined as a lean mass hyperresponder,
one should be lean normal BMI and have
very elevated blood low density
lipoprotein cholesterol. That's LDL
cholesterol from 190 mg per deciliter
and up as well as low triglyceride
levels below 80 mg per deciliter and
elevated high density lipoprotein
cholesterol or HDL cholesterol above 60
mg per deciliter. These three markers
high LDLC, low triglycerides and high
HDLC are called the triad. In addition,
all of these blood parameters, the
triad, occur on a very low carbohydrate
diet. So, in this study, the researchers
recruited 100 of these lean individuals
that had been on a very low carbohydrate
diet for several years and confirmed
that their LDL cholesterol had shot up
by at least 50%. then did artery imaging
to determine their baseline plaque in
their arteries and then again one year
later to quantify if there was arterial
plaque progression and how much. Now in
most studies published up to this point
the evidence resoundly points to LDL
particles of which apo is a component
cause plaque progression. But is that
necessarily always the case? Could a
group of people not experience such an
effect even though their LDL is
extremely high? I'll skip closer to the
initial punchline because there's
several things to mention. If we look at
the data, we see non-calcified plaque
volume on the left and non-calified and
calcified plaque on the right. Now, I'm
editing this video myself, so I can't
get all fancy with the editing. For
that, you're welcome to watch my
original video. It's unlisted, but it's
available in the description box. At any
rate, both measures indicate an increase
in plaque between baseline and one-year
results. So, we'll return to this. So,
yes, LMHRs still experience plaque
progression on average, but is that
plaque progression tracking with the
highly elevated APOB level representing
mostly by LDL particles in the blood?
Here again for better visual explanation
check out the original video but Apo B
levels in right ascending levels are on
the horizontal axis and the non-calified
plaque growth is on the vertical higher
is worse in short because the red line
doesn't move up much with increasing
APOB levels. There's no association. It
should look more like this. This is
relating to the same non-calcified
plaque on the vertical axis to calcified
plaque. So this would be interpreted as
if a person has plaque already,
specifically calcified plaque, there's
an association with greater plaque
growth over time. However, like I
mentioned, that is not due to apo. This
would be a bombshell if true because it
goes against the majority of the
literature, hundreds of studies that
indicate apo and LDL cause plaque
growth. Okay, so in pretty basic terms,
that's what the study showed. There's
some additional data that we'll get
into, but these data are where I came to
the two conclusions in my original post.
One, that LMHRs still develop plaque,
and two, that the plaque is not linked
to APOB, but linked to already present
calcified plaque. Now, those two
conclusions are correct based on what we
see in this study. Of course, I had my
own critiques that I'll reiterate in a
bit, but I did overlook one aspect and
then I was made aware of some of the
back and forth with the researchers on
Twitter. I don't use Twitter X, but
people brought it to my attention and I
did do a bit of Twittering or exing. The
latter sounds more like a homicidal
maniac. and I ran across some further
critiques that I'd like to include here,
as well as some responses by the
researchers. So, I will provide links to
the critiques and rebuttals in the the
description box. They're all excellent,
but I won't be able to go over all of
them, just the major points. So, let's
go over my oversight first. The
researchers pre-registered the study,
which means that they informed ahead of
time what their primary outcome is. This
is important because it locks in the
researchers to report on that outcome
and to focus their study on that
outcome. And we can see that the
researchers have their primary outcome
as the percent change in non-calcified
plaque volume. Now, the critique brought
forward by the likes of Dr. Nicole
Guess, Dr. Brad Stanfield, Dr. Kevin
Clatt and Alex Fleaf, all of which have
various formal medical and nutrition
backgrounds, is that the primary outcome
was not the highlight of the study when
it should have been. Instead, the
researchers focused on what predicts
plaque instead of is there plaque
according to the critiques. Now, if we
look at the graphs again, they mention
PAVV percent increase. That's was 0.8%
8%. But that's not the listed primary
outcome. It's percent of non-calcified
plaque volume, the left graph yet. The
percent is not shown and the numbers
aren't mentioned. This is where Twitter
twittered and asked for the numbers and
received an answer that alarmed some
people. An 18 mm cubed increase in
non-calcified plaque volume, which is
substantial. There was also a mention
that the researchers had predicted a 7
mm cubed increase over the year which
makes the 18.8 number 2 and a half times
greater than the predicted. However, I
should add that the 7 mm prediction is a
guess for a power calculation for a
group of people that have never been
studied in this way. So, it's really
just a shot in the fog and it's there to
determine how many participants they
need, including accounting for losing
participants over the year to detect
change if there is one. Either way, the
primary outcome change should have been
reported in the study. A related
critique is when comparing the percent
PAV, that's the right graph, which
showed a 0.8% increase in plaque, those
values also don't look altogether
favorable. So if we look at these data,
we see that the average growth of 0.8%
in this study, then we see a few
different studies looking at different
groups of people and their plaque
progression calculated to be per year or
annualized. One critique has been that
looking at the average of 0.8% and
stacking that up against some of these
other groups, they were progressing at a
similar rate. Now, most of these groups
of people are people with diabetes, high
blood pressure, high cholesterol, and so
on. So, if lean individuals who are
otherwise healthy yet have this triad
that we discussed earlier, are
progressing at a similar speed, well,
that's pretty serious. Dr. Nick Norwitz
and colleagues do have some answers,
some explained in this interview, which
is also linked for you to watch in full,
and some that I'll pull from the depths
of Twitterdom in a bit to reinforce Dr.
Norawitz's point I was saying like part
of the concern has been that maybe some
of the message has been you know that
less hyperresponders are safe and you
talked about plaque progression not
being correlated with LDL but the key
being that there was plaque progression
and I think that's one of the messages
that maybe I don't know has gotten lost
or or or people are concerned isn't
being portrayed enough but I mean there
was plaque progression but now the
question is what does that mean and
that's the harder part to answer when
you have a very heterogeneic
um population like you're saying. Yeah.
You know, I it's funny because a lot of
the messages you'll hear from me and
from other people's are actually
consistent. They don't sound consistent.
But if I say a majority did not have
rapid black progression, that is totally
accurate. It's totally accurate based on
these data and the next paper we have
under review. We'll go into a little bit
more details there about what this means
clinically. Um, and we're also quite
clear, like if you watch my video, I say
very clearly, does this mean lean mass
hyperresponders are immune to
cardiovascular disease? No, it does not
mean that. So, me and my colleagues
Dave, Adrian, Matt Budof, other
co-authors have been consistent about
that message. And I think this is one of
those moments where social media does
what social media does and puts the more
nuance messages through a filter of
social media and caricatures get
generated and then they hold it up as
look, you know, Nick, Dave, Adrian,
they're saying X and they're like, no,
no, we're saying Y. Like, ah, see,
they're saying X. I'm like, now where
are we at? I don't know what the back
and forth has been on social media and
its completeness, but that last point is
certainly something that can happen on
the old socials. But the larger point
that Dr. Norowitz points out is that the
majority of of the participants did not
have rapid plaque progression and spoke
to heterogeneity in the data, meaning
that some people experienced extremely
fast plaque progression and some
experienced slower progression. And we
can actually see that
here. Those with already present plaque
have extremely fast plaque development,
but keep in mind that was still a
minority of the group. The majority had
much slower plaque progression. Those
with zero calcium plaque progressed at
0.5%. So, still progression, but slower
than the average and much slower than
the hyper growers. Now, I should also
note that most rebuttals, critiques to
this study have focused almost
exclusively on the 0.8% value, the
average value, and haven't mentioned the
slower progression in those without
calcium plaque. Still, in the context of
the other studies there, most are in
somewhat health compromised individuals.
So, the rate of plaque progression is
still very likely greater even in the
slowest plaque developing group. then
when compared to a completely ideal
group of individuals, something that
I'll touch on later because this was one
of my critique critiques in my previous
video. Now, I also mentioned some
answers from Twitter, which Dr. Norowitz
also put together from Dr. Budof, the
senior researcher here. It's true that
there's been consistency by the
researchers. They've all stated that
plaque still progresses and it is true
that the plaque progression is slower in
the majority of the participants, but I
would argue that is only relative to the
faster progressives and maybe relative
to completely metabolically compromised
individuals leaving them uh a bit in a
middle ground. As a final point, Dr.
Budof was also asked about the plaque
progression in an interview. Now you're
going to see the same table that we've
been referencing and here is what his
answer was in its entirety. Yeah. So, so
now if we look at supplemental table one
from the keto CTA study and we look at
the all comers that with the baseline
PAV is 1.6 and the delta PAV is is 0.8
and that's for all 100 participants.
Some people are interpreting that as
saying that is a
50% relative increase which is higher
than any trial has ever shown and is
incredibly concerning. And if you look
at the numbers it they are correct. It
is a 50% relative percentage increase.
So how do you how do you interpret that
type of change? Well well one you can't
do it based on a percent because the
denominator was very low. The
denominator was lower than most other
trials. So when you have a low
denominator, any number looks big. For
example, if I tell you you had a calcium
score of one and it went up to a calcium
score of three, you might you might say
that's great. One and three are both
very low calcium scores and therefore
I'm in great shape and over two years or
one year that was a minimal change. But
if you calculate a percent change,
that's 200%. And if I tell you your
clock is going up by 200%, you should be
panicked and you should So I think
misinterpreting the data, we don't
calculate a percent PAV percentage
change over time. Uh because the
denominators are so important when you
think about those things. The other
thing that you have to remember with the
keto study is we took in patients who
were across all types of plaque but were
on no other medical therapies. So they
weren't on anti-hypertensives and they
weren't on statins and they weren't on
anti-inflammatories or aspirin. So we
took a a natural history a a treatment
naive population and said what is the
effect of a high LDL by by the induced
by the keto diet on plaque progression
and we found that it was not related to
the LDL. So that is the answer of the
question. The fact that some of these
patients had a lot of plaque and and
should be on a statin or that the that
they had a lot of plaque and they should
have been on other therapies to slow
down plaque progression is a whole
another question and and we have
recommended that they go on other
therapies once we identified them as
having plaque. But but this was a true
treatment naive population that was just
using keto diet for overall health and
we thought that they were all lean
healthy people and some of them had a
lot of plaque at baseline. Um which to
me was you know I think you know a
difference between the other studies.
All the other studies use two three four
five background therapies to treat
patients. So you can't say a treatment
naive population progressed more than a
treated population and be surprised.
That that's just too naive to to even
think about. Okay, two main points
there. First, the question is put out
there as a critique based on relative
increase in plaque. And I agree with Dr.
Budof's point that looking at relative
increases yields astronomical numbers
when the baseline plaque is well already
low. However, the critique that I've
seen has been about the absolute values,
not the relative values. So, this
doesn't actually address the primary
criticism that I've seen repeated. On
the other hand, the second point about
LMHR individuals being a treatment naive
population, as in not taking any drugs
or any additional interventions, would
be an excellent one if only the
comparison groups were in equally
assumed lower risk individuals. And even
if we restrict our comparison to those
with no calcified plaque, the
progression is still not ideal. So all
in all, I agree in theory, but I don't
think that it addresses the critiques
offered, especially the aforementioned
Dr. Guest, Dr. Clatt, and Mr. Leaf.
Anyway, there is a way to find out the
answer, and it's the primary critique
that I've had since learning about this
study a year and a half ago. We need an
adequate parallel control group. People
who have normal blood pressure, healthy
weight, normal cholesterol, normal blood
sugar, and so on, and compare the rate
of plaque progression in those
individuals against the LMHR
individuals. That's really the only way
that we'll get clear answers on the
level of risk by plaque
progression. But like I mentioned last
video, this stuff isn't cheap to finance
and it takes a whole lot of work. So, we
can critique all that we want, but we
should also acknowledge the amount of
work that has to go into this research,
too. Anyway, let's move on to the final
major critique that I'll cover here, and
then we'll put everything together. The
final one was the lack of association
between APOB and plaque development.
Again, if that holds true, that is a
bombshell. Now, I've seen far fewer
critiques of this data than of the last
point, but there have been a few. In
fact, Dr. Norowitz brings up a great
point that does seem a bit hypocritical
at first glance. So, to set this up,
it's been said over and over again that
the greater one's blood LDL and APOB
levels are, the greater one's
cardiovascular disease risk because
there's a linear concentration burden.
As LDL and apo go up, there's an assumed
faster plaque progression because you
have so many more particles that can
cross into the subendothelium and form
plaque. And yet now some of the
critiques are that there's a threshold
level and once you cross that threshold,
the relationship may not show. Well, I
think the point of contention that I've
seen is that there's a threshold level
that once you're above a threshold
level, it doesn't matter. Like it
doesn't matter if you're 600 or 200.
It's just all so high that it
contributes the same. I mean there's no
real evidence I don't think to support
that. But it's a hypothesis, right? It's
a hypothesis that should be entertained
just like any other. I suppose. But I've
never heard that prior to this point in
time, prior to these data like that will
be a new supposition that there's a
saturation effect for LDL levels such
that if you have a a 200 or a 10,000, it
doesn't make a difference. that actually
caught the counters a lot of the
pre-existing notions pre-existing like
status quo thinking around Apple B where
they talk about Apple B or LDL
milligrams per deciliter deciliter year
exposure so multiplying the amount by
the duration so if you're saying there's
a saturation effect you're effectively
taking the preponderance of evidence
that everybody talks about and throwing
it out in order to make an argument I
just want to point out that irony
because it's not subtle that critique on
the face of It is weak and I have to
agree we can't move the goalposts on
that one especially when it's been
repeated so many times. In fact, I had
this same discussion with Dave Feldman,
another one of the researchers and
spearheads of the lean mass
hyperresponder movement. Yet, there are
some other critiques I'd like to bring
up for completeness.
For example, one critique is that the
researchers are only including the top
band of high LDL as there's no one with
moderate or low levels of blood LDL
APOB. As a result, there isn't enough
difference inside the group to create a
relationship. Another possibility is the
fact that the study is powered for its
primary outcome. So plaque progression
remember the 7 mm cubed that we
discussed earlier that doesn't mean that
it's powered as in has enough
participants to detect a relationship in
APOB. However, the first critique I
don't find too convincing especially as
some people have used smoking as another
example. If you smoke three packs a day,
smoking four packs a day isn't going to
lead to any detectable increase in risk
of cancer because, well, the majority of
the effect occurs from three packs.
Generally, that's true, but smoking
doesn't necessarily follow the same
rules as OPO B where increasing blood
levels is ever more a problem. Now, the
second argument is a possibility. It's
one of those situations where we just
don't know. It's the same issue with any
secondary outcome, which is what this
is. Now, there might be some other
critiques, but they certainly haven't
been as vocal as the first point. So,
I'll leave it there on that front. Okay.
Now, all that being said, where does
that leave things? Now, before that, I
mentioned this in the last video, but
I'll be doing a live session that will
include more discussion with the
Physionic Insider community along with
uh many of my other analyses. If you're
interested in joining, the link is in
the description. Well, the emotionality
around this topic has been really
something to behold. I mean, certainly
for good reason in some respects, but we
can say a few things
definitively. Revisiting my previous
conclusions, as I stated then and state
now, lean mass hypersponders still
develop plaque in the arteries. Now,
some added context indicates that some
develop plaque at an extraordinary rate
and others develop at a more tempered
rate.
Another thing that we know is we don't
know why. Keep in mind these are
supposed to be metabolically healthy
individuals and if the apo lack of
relationship stands that leaves a gaping
hole to find out what is causing this
atherosclerosis risk. As for what we
aren't entirely sure about, APOB is
still not correlated to plaque
progression and critiques are less
obvious. Although addressing those that
do exist, i.e. like an underpowered
analysis, for example, would go a ways
to bolster or weaken these findings. A
few final things to acknowledge. The
researchers should have reported the
primary outcome including in the
abstract and based on the current
evidence that everyone agrees on. If I
were a lean mass hyperresponder, I would
certainly try to get a CT angiogram to
determine my current risk if there's
plaque or not. Then due to the varying
levels of uncertainty related to this
apo relationship to plaque progression
and considering that I'm lean and
otherwise healthy, I would tackle my sky
high LDL levels just to be safe until
more of these questions can be answered.
Okay, that's the end. But let me also
quick say thanks to all the people who
commented under my takeown notice of my
last video. I did not expect such an
overwhelmingly supportive note. Anyway,
the goal has always been to get to the
truth, even if I have to correct myself,
and constructive criticism is part of
the process. So, thanks again, and
thanks for your support. By the way,
apparently, we actually don't consume
spiders in our sleep. That was a myth
purposefully propagated to show how
easily misinformation can spread. But if
one did get consumed, there's a chance
it could control your brain. There's
always a chance. See you next time.
[Music]